Register of the Timothy A. Beresney (Timofei Avvakumovich Bereznii) Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Timothy A. Beresney papers,
1929-1958
2001C25
Beresney, Timothy A., 1891-1959
3 microfilm reels (0.45 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, and printed matter, relating to Russian émigré affairs.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biographical Note
Russian émigré journalist in the United States; editor, Nash put' and Russkoe obozrenie.
Scope and Content Note
Beresney was a journalist and editor of several émigré periodicals, among them Nash put', Russkii vestnik, and Russkoe obozrenie. The collection contains correspondence relating to his editorial duties at two of these periodicals, as well as his writings on Soviet education and English and Russian-language study guides. There is also a work by his wife, Polina V. Swatikoff, on Joseph de Maistre in Russia (SUBJECT FILE).
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Russians--United States.; Journalism--United States.; Russia.; United States.
Occupations
Journalists.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1952-1954. (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Letters and cards relating to Beresney's activity as editor of Nash put' and Russkoe obozrenie. Correspondents include Archbishop Leontii of Chicago, S. Korsunets, and others
- WRITINGS, [1929]-1958 and undated (Box 1-3)
  Books and articles, arranged chronologically by title
  - "Civic Education in Soviet Russia," n.d.
    Typescript
    - Part I (Folder 1: 2)
    - Part II (Folder 1: 3)
    - Appendix I (Folder 1: 4)
    - Appendix II (Folder 1: 5)
    - Appendix III (Folder 1: 6)
  - "Polnaia khrestomatiia po russkomu iazyku," n.d. (Folder 1: 7)
    Holograph and typescript (two drafts)
  - "Polnaia khrestomatiia po russkomu iazyku" (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
  - "Izuchenie zernovykh khoziaistv v zasushlivykh raionakh SASh gruppoi agronomov Zernotresta," [1929]. (Folder 2: 3)
  - "Angliiskii iazyk," 1950.
    - Part I (Folder 2: 4-6)
    - Part II (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "200-letie pervoi russkoi grammatiki," Russkoe obozrenie, 1955 September 17. (Folder 3: 2)
  - Russkii muzhik i vodorodnaia bomba, 1958. (Folder 3: 3)
    Printed copy
- SUBJECT FILE, 1950-1955 and undated (Box 3)
  Bulletins, leaflets, and writings, arranged alphabetically by heading
  - de Maistre, Joseph. (Folder 3: 4)
    Typescript by Polina V. Swatikoff (Beresney's wife) entitled "Joseph de Maistre et la Russie," n.d.
  - Religion. (Folder 3: 5)
    Leaflets and brochures relating to Russian Orthodoxy, Dukhobors, and general religious topics
  - Russia--History, 862-1698, n.d. (Folder 3: 6)
    Unattributed article on the subject submitted for publication in one of Beresney's periodicals
  - Soviet Union--Foreign policy (Folder 3: 7)
  - Miscellany (Folder 3: 8)
- PHOTOGRAPH, n.d. (Folder 3: 9)
  One print depicting a monument to Russian-Americans killed in the Second World War